Say that we have our predicted state x described by a Gaussian distribution.
予測状態xがあり ガウス分布によって記述されるものとします
If we map this Gaussian to a nonlinear function h,
このガウス分布を 非線形関数hにマッピングした場合
then the result is not a Gaussian distribution anymore.
結果は ガウス分布ではなくなります
So the Kalman filter is not applicable anymore.
カルマンフィルターは 適用できなくなります
And in order to visualize the impact of this nonlinear transformation,
また この非線形変換の影響を 視覚化するために
I've created a simple test.
簡単なテストを作成しました
I've generated a list of 10,000 random values drawn from
10,000のランダムな値の リストを生成しました
a normal distribution with a mean of 0 and a standard deviation of 3.
これらは平均0 標準偏差3の 正規分布から選ばれた値です
And here is the histogram of these values.
これがこれらの値の ヒストグラムです
And you can see that it follows a Gaussian shape.
見ると分かるように これはガウス分布の形状に従っています
Then for each of these values xi, I have computed the corresponding h over xi.
次に これらの値xiのそれぞれについて xiに対応するhを計算しました
And in my case, h is the arctangent of xi, which
この例では hはxiのアークタンジェントであり
is a nonlinear function that is also used in our radar measurement model.
レーダー測定モデルでも使用される 非線形関数です
The result is stored in an output list.
結果は出力リストに保存されます
And finally, I use my output list to generate a new histogram.
そして最後に 出力リストを使用して 新しいヒストグラムを生成します
What we see here is that the resulting distribution is not a Gaussian any more,
これを見ると結果としての 分布はガウス分布ではなくなります
because of the nonlinearity of h.
hの非線形のためです
Moreover, the transformed density cannot be represented in closed form.
さらに変換後の密度は 閉じた形式で表すことはできません
So Kalman filter update equations are not applicable here.
そのためカルマンフィルターは 適用できません
How can we fix that?
これを修正するにはどうすればよいでしょうか
A possible solution is to linearize the h(x) function.
可能なソリューションは h(x)関数を線形化することです
And that's the key idea of the so-called extended Kalman filter.
また、これは拡張カルマンフィル ターの基本的な概念です
So we have to approximate our measurement function h by a linear
測定関数hを 線形関数で概算する必要があり
function which is tangent to h at the mean location of the original Gaussian.
これは元のガウス分布の 平均位置でのhのタンジェントです
So I repeated the same test.
同じテストを繰り返しました
I used the same list of randomly sampled values from a normal distribution.
正規分布からの同じランダムなサンプル値の リストを使用しました
But instead of applying the nonlinear function h,
しかし 非線形関数hを 適用する代わりに
all the xi values were passed through the linear approximation of h.
すべてのxi値が hの線型近似を通して渡されました
And we can see now that unlike the non linear case, this time,
これを見ると 非線形の場合とは違って
our resulting distribution retained the Gaussian nature.
結果としての分布は ガウス分布の性質を残しています
So how do we linearize a nonlinear function?
ではどのように 非線形関数を線形化したらよいでしょうか
The extended Kalman filter uses a method called first order Taylor expansion.
拡張カルマンフィルターは 一次テイラー拡張と呼ばれるメソッドを使用します
So what we do is we first evaluate the nonlinear function h at the mean
ここでするのは まず 非線形関数hを平均位置µで評価します
location mu, which is the best estimate of our predicted distribution.
これは予測分布の 最善予測です
And then we extrapolate the line with slope around mu.
次に線をµの周辺の 傾きで外挿します
And this slope is given by the first derivative of h.
この傾きは hの最初の微分係数によって与えられます
Similarly, extended Kalman filters implement exactly the same linearization
同様に拡張カルマンフィルターは xの状態遷移fも非線形のときと
when the state transition f of x is also nonlinear.
まったく同じ 線形化を実装します
So in the next quiz, I would like
次のクイズでは
you to compute as a practice the linear equation for a given function.
練習として 与えられた関数の線形式を 計算してもらいます